All right.
And next up we have Doctor Bridget,
kids from Oakland University
with once Upon an algorithm.
The book authors
AI folk theories in the standardization
of creative practice.
Hello.
In his 2017 book Once Upon an Algorithm,
Martin Herwig introduces
general readers to basic concepts
and computing using analogies of common
fables and fairy tales.
In doing so, Erwin's
interest is in making computer science
intelligible outside its discipline
and in showing how skills like problem
solving and concepts
like algorithms are not just specific
to software engineering and coding,
but rather part of an everyday life.
I've used the same title for this project,
which takes a similar approach
of looking at the stories that we tell
about algorithms
and artificial intelligence,
the commonly shared folk theories
that have evolved in recent years
as AI users and skeptics grapple
with what they know and don't know
about the tools
that are circulating right now.
And this is part of a larger project
focusing on the romance industry,
some a bit of an outlier here
because I'm setting a commercial genre,
but it's a heavily book driven industry
with lots of self-publishing,
and it's a digitized space
where communities are pretty much
operating entirely digitally and socially.
In the first stage of this project,
I conducted an internet based
survey of readers
about their attitudes toward generative
AI at different stages of writing.
Their attitudes toward authors uses
right from pre writing,
like outlining and brainstorming,
to actually generating text,
to turning completed manuscripts
into translations
like we just talked about
or creating audiobooks.
In addition, I've joined numerous writers
groups on social media where authors
discuss the specifics of how they use
various tools, mostly Claude,
and how they interact with the outputs
of those tools, if at all,
how their incomes have been augmented
by faster output and automation.
I've also just started the process of
demoing some AI writing tools for writers.
I'm really interested in the way that they
they're like
mostly custom GPT with cool interfaces,
but they market themselves
as being proprietary
and as doing something different from what
you could get using
Claude or ChatGPT on your own.
That's kind of beyond the scope of today's
talk, though.
I'm also currently in the process
of conducting interviews
with romance authors from around the world
to find out how they're using AI,
and if they're not, why not?
So through all this research,
I've observed several common
folk theories or informal beliefs
about how AI tools work based on
user experiences and
traded gossip,
rather than deep technical knowledge.
Folk theories are mental representations
that humans use to structure experience,
and they're often full of inconsistencies
gaps in idiosyncratic quirks.
These folk theories are circulated
around social networks, and they become
community wisdom that shapes
how writers use and expect other writers
to use AI tools, and how writing workshops
and AI interfaces
promise to help authors, often
selling these theories as best practices.
These folk theories also shape
how readers engage
or disengage with particular ebooks.
The idea of an algorithmic folk
theory has been taken up in media studies,
digital humanities,
studies of human computer interaction HCI
for more than ten years,
with various studies focusing on the way
people explain and understand
recommendation algorithms,
newsfeed on social media,
content moderation, etc.
more recently,
some of us have been applying this concept
to the way we see
people attempting to explain AI tools.
I'm far from the first person
to make this connection
between algorithmic folk theory
and AI folk theory.
HCI studies have recently begun
to pay more attention
to the e-book ecosystem
and to self-publishing
some people, even specifically focusing
on the romance industry like me.
But no one is yet focused on the idea
of how these AI folk theories
specifically shape the culture of writing
and publishing ebooks
and what impact that has on the market.
So extending the concept
of the algorithmic folk theory,
or as Tanya Boucher
calls it, the algorithmic imaginary into
AI only seemed logical after I kept seeing
authors trade advice with each other
about how to finesse prompts for Claude,
why Claude is better than Gemini
or ChatGPT, or explain to each other,
often incorrectly,
how text generators work,
and seeing readers
express their own concerns
about plagiarism and slop.
This is very much research and progress,
so I welcome your ideas and your feedback.
But here's where I am so far.
I'll start with the most obvious
folk theory,
which I'm sure everyone has encountered
on the reader's end.
It involves lists of AI isms
that are believed to be telltale
signs that attacks was generated by AI
in academia.
Two years ago,
it was students use of the word delve
that professors decided was a sign.
Their essays had been written
by ChatGPT previously.
It was the use of em dashes, I mean, I,
I encountered several versions of this.
One was that overuse of em
dashes was indicative of generated text.
Another theory was
it was substitution of hyphens for m
dashes and maybe vice versa.
In 2025, Sam Altman admitted on a podcast
that OpenAI had added more frequent
use of m dashes to ChatGPT
because they thought people liked them.
But later that year, OpenAI announced
it was lessening
the frequency of their use
after public complaints.
So that one does appear
to be somewhat true.
But of course, the use of M as a flair in
writing comes from classic literary texts
that llms have been built upon, like here
we have Emily Dickinson and a
line from White Noise with the word delve.
Right?
So, like all AI isms,
it's less a quirk of a chatbot
and more reflective of the idiosyncrasies
of certain human writing,
which may be amplified
with particular prompts or outputs.
On writer's end, folk theories
abound about how to prompt your favorite
AI writing tool.
To avoid the incorporation of these
AI isms, writers encourage each other
to upload these lists to their preferred
chat bot, to train it, not to use them,
lest their work be readily identified
as AI generated by a reader
who may then leave
negative reviews or report
a book for takedown on Amazon.
Some tools also feature lists of these
AI isms, with the promise
that their particular tool,
which usually involves
a hefty subscription fee, is smarter
at avoiding them than free
versions of ChatGPT novel crafter,
for instance, lists
the words palpable, tangible and raced
as three primary examples of AI isms.
But such lists are not scientific
or precise,
and that this particular list has no date
attached to it is especially concerning,
since we know most commonly used text
generators no longer
operate on closed training sets.
Writers desire to avoid AI isms
is deeply connected to the phenomenon of
AI witch hunts, which I think are keynote
sort of, you know, danced around here.
I've written about this elsewhere,
and it's kind of
outside
the scope of our presentation today.
But I do think it's worth noting that
sharing lists of words, phrases,
punctuation that indicate text generation,
it's a major part of AI folk theory.
Another folk theory views Claude
as temperamental
and endows it with personality.
So, Katherine, this feeds really nicely
off of your presentation theories.
Explain how to prompt around these moods
and authors celebrate
when Claude is cooperative and helpful
as a sign that they're good at using AI,
or that Claude likes them.
Personally,
I don't think this one should come
as a surprise to those of us who study
chatbots or voice assistants.
Or we had a lovely panel
about Eliza yesterday.
So anyone who's familiar
with the Eliza effect, right?
We anthropomorphize technology,
which AI chatbots
have been specifically designed for.
They interact with us
like friends and colleagues.
They're imbued with human names
and women's voices and friendly rejoinder.
So it's only logical that when they don't
perform exactly as we expect,
rather than seeing it as a problem
with our prompting, we view them
as having personalities or moods
that might fluctuate.
In prior studies of how users interact
with social media platforms, researchers
similarly found that users would interpret
algorithms as emotional,
or that the algorithms
were interpreting users emotions
in their recommendation of content.
So again, what's happening with
AI isn't necessarily different than what
preceded it with different technology,
but nonetheless, it helps us understand
why writers make the choices
they do when using AI tools.
And it tells us where we can encourage
more AI literacy, which is the point.
Michael Ridley is similarly made
about algorithmic folk
theories and algorithmic literacy.
In the interest of time,
I'm just going to leave it at those two,
because ultimately, which specific
folk theories authors have come up with
is less important than the impact
of trading this folk wisdom
and full theories, the impact that it has
on digital writing and publishing.
The circulation of lists of AI isms
has exacerbated a problem wherein readers
feel overly
confident calling out what they perceive
as AI generated text,
which can have an impact on a writer,
sales and social status
within the community at the same time,
because these lists tell writers
what to avoid or or what
to edit out of their work,
there's a standardization
of writing to meet perceived market
demands,
and a common criticism of generated texts
is that its outputs are standard
and bland and unoriginal.
But writing to avoid being used of using
AI might also result in writing
that is bland, standard, and unoriginal,
because potential creative flourishes
might be perceived
as having been generated by a chat bot.
When I began this research, it seemed like
the conclusion it was pointing to
was that all these folk theories
that are presented as best practices
are standardizing writing and publishing,
and I expected to argue
that there's real shame in that,
a decline in creative possibilities,
but that perhaps it was something
understandable in a general like romance,
because it's a commercial genre.
However,
as I've gotten deeper into this project,
when I actually see happening
as a literary house of cards,
authors are constantly trading tips,
giving workshops to each other, writing
blog posts, and posting social media
videos about what does and doesn't work
to attract and sell books,
the best way to write, how to use Amazon
more effectively, etc.
like all of this exists
separate from AOO or Nonuse,
and there's a lot of culture
about how this there's a lot of research
about how this culture of sharing creates
a community.
What better school refers to as networked
reading, or what other scholars
have referred to as the relational labor
of being an e-book author?
Today, when I counter all these advice,
tips and posts, am often baffled at
the lack of evidence being used to support
any particular theory or advice.
But I seem to be an outlier in a community
where folk wisdom is taken for granted.
So as authors have turned to AI assistants
for assistance or for text generation,
they're trying to interact
with a complex technology
and they swap advice to each other.
Full theories about how best to prompt
why certain prompts do or don't work,
what kind of filtering and safeguards
their favorite
AI tools have in place,
and how to work around it.
How to work around getting an output
that will be pinged as AI generated
among those who refuse to AI,
those same theories circulate as ways to
spot the telltale signs of an author's
use of AI, or as proof of why
writing with AI isn't as good,
and so series that may or may not
be rooted in technical truth
become accepted as objective reality.
The existence of AI folk theories
shouldn't really surprise us.
Rather, it's an extension of an industry
that has been built on a sharing culture
in which peer to peer advice and
recommendations become community wisdom.
Thanks.